# 撇着走 你看
Look, just glide.
# 给师父多盛点鸡蛋
Spoon more of the eggs for your master.
# 黄豆 头天泡好的 半斤
0.5 jin (250g) of soybeans, soaked since yesterday.
# 干豆半斤 对
- 0.5 jin dry soybeans? - Yes.
# 三斤水 半斤豆
3 jin (1.5kg) of water, 0.5 jin soybeans
# 泡了一宿
They have been soaked for a night.
# 齐活 过箩
Done! Now go through the strainer.
# 一点油都不能粘吗 对不能有油
- Absolutely no oil in this? - Correct, absolutely no oil.
# 豆香味真浓
Such a rich aroma of soybean.
# 这浆磨好了
The soy milk has been ground.
# 开火熬一下 熬开
Bring it to a boil and keep it boiling for a while.
# 这浆纯
Very pure soy milk.
# 这是最优质的植物蛋白 堪比牛奶
This is the highest quality vegetable protein, as good as cow milk.
# 这浆 香味出来了
Such good milk. The aroma has come out.
# 一直搅着 千万不能叫它扑了
Keep on stirring. Never let it overflow.
# 第一次开锅 这是个假开
This is the first time boiling, a fake one.
# 一定要叫它真开
You have to let it boil for real.
# 两次开锅到三次开锅  煮透了
Let it boil for two or three times until thoroughly cooked.
# 把沫子撇撇
Get rid of the foam.
# 咱这边小火这么熬着
We’ll keep this on gentle heat.
# 把豆腐王放到碗里头
Put Doufuwang into the bowl.
# 专门点豆腐 豆腐脑的
It is specifically used to gel tofu.
# 从超市 市场有卖的
You can buy it in supermarkets or markets.
# 一包正好三克 倒到碗里头
3 grams in each sachet. Pour it into the bowl.
# 这是关键所在 没这个成不了豆腐脑
This is the key. Tofu will not become pudding without it.
# 少搁点水 澥一下 澥透了
Put a little bit of water in and thoroughly dissolve it.
# 关键来了 垫上毛巾给它砸起来
Here comes the most important part. Hold the pot up with towels.
# 这是关键 你一冲就行
This is the key part. Just pour it in.
# 你就这样冲就能冲开了
The gelatin will be mixed evenly as you pour like this.
# 这豆腐脑
This is going to be tofu pudding.
# 盖盖儿 五到十分钟 齐活
Put the lid on. Wait for 5-10 min. Done.
# 这时候咱们打卤 两不耽误
During this time, we can make the sauce.
# 黄花 木耳 香菇
Citron daylily, black fungus, shiitake mushroom.
# 这豆腐脑好吃不好吃
Whether the tofu pudding tastes delicious or not,
# 就在你那锅卤了啊
all depends on this sauce you make.
# 葱花下锅 炸出香味来
Fry chopped green onion until it brings out the aroma.
# 香菇水留着
Keep the water used for shiitake mushrooms.
# 家里有炖骨头的汤也可以搁点
If you have already got bone broth, you can put some here.
# 咱今天没有就不搁了
We don’t have it today, so we’ll skip that.
# 这时候把香菇跟黄花煸一下
Now we stir fry the shiitake mushrooms and citron daylily.
# 给它煸点香味出来
Stir fry until you can smell a bit of their aroma there.
# 酱油烹出香味
Cook soy sauce until its aroma is out.
# 木耳下进去
Put the black fungus in.
# 很简单 又好吃 又营养
Easy, tasty and nutritious.
# 加点香菇水
Add some shiitake mushroom water.
# 香菇水底下就不要了
Skip the bottom (sediment) of the water.
# 味出来了 这酱油的香 炝锅的香 诱人
The aroma from the flash-fried soy sauce came out, so tempting.
# 一定要烹
It must be boiled.
# 盐 卤要咸点
Salt. The sauce needs to be salty.
# 白胡椒粉
White pepper ground.
# 来点淀粉
Put in some starch.
# 勾点芡
Thicken it.
# 颜色浅点 来点颜色
The colour is not dark enough, so we add some colour.
# 老抽 调点色
Dark soy sauce to adjust the colour.
# 俩鸡蛋 这个鸡蛋得泼
Two eggs. The stirred eggs need to be sprinkled.
# 不能攉拢 就等着吃了
- Do not stir. - Now we are just waiting to eat.
# 准备出锅 关火
We are going to take it out of the pot. Stop the heat.
# 这时候就叫这鸡蛋慢慢的熟了
Now the eggs are cooked slowly.
# 你看这是成片 它不散
Look, they are connected into pieces. They don’t break into tiny bits.
# 你看 片儿就出来了
See? Now you get the pieces.
# 来这么一碗 现出锅的油条一吃
Have a bowl of this with Youtiao (deep-fried dough sticks) just out of the pot.
# 出锅了
It’s out of the pot.
# 来 师父 小亮
Come on, master and Xiao Liang.
# 吃你这碗豆腐脑 就当早点了
I’ll have a bowl of your tofu pudding as breakfast.
# 先给师父来吧
Let’s spoon it for our master first.
# 撇着走
Glide.
# 一层一层的
One layer on top of another layer.
# 一碗
This is one bowl.
# 这卤高级了 给师父多盛点鸡蛋
This is a luxurious sauce. Spoon more of the eggs for your master.
# 这卤还有鸡蛋呢 成本多高啊
This sauce has eggs in it. How lavish!
# 还差一东西
One thing is missing.
# 这藏着宝贝呢
You’ve got hidden treasure here!
# 早上买的油条 烤箱里熥一下
The Youtiao I bought in the morning. Warm it up in the oven.
# 得讲究
You gotta live with a style.
# 这夜宵吃油条也是别有风味儿
It feels special to have Youtiao as a midnight snack.
# 够嫩啊 师父 这够嫩
This is very tender, master.
# 爱吃辣椒的加点辣椒
Chilli lovers can add some chilli in it.
# 这是比外边卖的好吃
This does taste better than the ones in restaurants.
# 料足 嫩
It has sufficient ingredients, and tastes tender.
# 这豆花真的嫩 入口就化了
This tofu pudding is so tender that it melts once put in mouth.
# 但是你看着还挺成型
But it somewhat has a shape.
# 老鼠爱大米 这是油条爱豆腐脑
Mice love rice. Youtiao loves tofu pudding.
# 油条这么吃 沾一下
You eat Youtiao in this way. Dip it here.
# 一看就地道
You look very authentic.
# 吃的舒服
It feels comfy eating this.
# 跟外边不一样
Different with the ones you can buy from restaurants.
# 这个豆腐脑我吃出我当年的感觉了
Eating this tofu pudding is bringing me back the kind of feeling that I felt many years ago.
# 让我这想起了回忆
It has brought back memories to me.
# 咱们街道办里有一个网友刘sir
There is a netizen, Mr. Liu, in our sub-district office.
# 想让您给讲讲
He would like you to talk about,
# 常见的
common
# 食盐种类和用法
classification and usage of salt.
# 我们在烹饪里边的盐
The salt we use in cooking
# 大体上分为两种
are mainly distributed into two types.
# 一种就是粗盐
One of them is coarse salt.
# 大粒儿盐
Large grain salt.
# 现在还有一种
Now we have another type of salt.
# 就是我们常吃的细盐
That is fine salt, which we have everyday.
# 细盐里边的内容也挺多
Fine salt has much content.
# 有的加一些香料
Some add a few spices.
# 有的为了低用盐的一些消费者
Some appeal to the customers who want less saltiness.
# 可能这盐不是很咸
Therefore the salt is not very salty.
# 另外还有好多
There are many other kinds.
# 比如说玫瑰盐
Such as Himalayan salt.
# 还有好多生吃蘸料的
There are many for dipping raw food.
# 辣椒盐
Chilli salt.
# 花椒盐
Sichuan pepper salt.
# 但真正我们常用的盐就是大粒盐
But the salt we use the most often is actually large grain salt.
# 大粒盐干什么使
What do we use large grain salt for?
# 四川腌豆瓣酱
It can be used to cure Sichuan Doubanjiang.
# 做泡菜用的很广泛
It is widely used in pickling.
# 它用的全是大粒儿盐
The kind of salt they use in these is the large grain salt.
# 大粒盐里边含有有硝
Large grain salt contains nitrate.
# 这硝呢它是起防腐作用的
Nitrate here is used as a preservative.
# 另外我们腌火腿
Besides, when we cure hams,
# 腌一些咸肉腊肉
or for salt-cured meat,
# 都用大粒盐
we use large grain salt.
# 包括有的地区做黄酱
Some places use it to make yellow soybean paste,
# 做酱油
or soy sauce.
# 它起的作用是什么呢
What does it do here?
# 比如腌的火腿
For example, when curing ham,
# 它能使肉质发红
it can make the meat redden,
# 保存期比较长
and delay the expiration date.
# 有的还得把它搁到房梁底下
With some of them, you would have to put them under the beam of the house,
# 在火上进行熏
and fumigate it on fire.
# 熏也是一种保鲜的方法
Fumigation is a preservation method too.
# 作为细盐来说
As for fine salt,
# 就是我们家庭炒菜的盐了
they are just what we use in cooking domestically,
# 有些我们的粉丝网友也看到了
Some of our fans have noticed
# 说大爷上次做的肉饼
that they asked about the meat pie Da Ye made,
# 是不是搁盐搁多了
that if he had put too much salt.
# 这个问题我发现了很多次
I’ve noticed this problem many times.
# 我刚开始我就放了一定的盐
I have put certain amount of salt in the beginning.
# 就按照我凭经验估计的盐
I estimated the amount according to my experience.
# 一点都不咸
But it did not taste salty at all.
# 我就拿这手蘸点水
So I dipped my hand with a bit of water,
# 蘸了一手指头盐搁我嘴里头
then dipped salt on my finger tip and put it into my mouth.
# 不能说一点咸味没有啊
I wouldn’t say it’s totally without saltiness,
# 就根本就不咸
but it was really not very salty.
# 就跟着我们吃个咸菜似的
It felt like eating pickles.
# 那么一个咸味
That level of saltiness.
# 所以我在做菜当中
So when I cook,
# 就增加了一倍的盐
I would double the amount of salt.
# 我们盐业
Talking about the salt industry.
# 因为它也是一个
Its existence is also
# 为了社会经济的发展
for the purpose of the development of society and economy.
# 经常在家吃饭的可能吃两袋盐
If you always eat at home, perhaps you consume two bags of salt.
# 结果这个盐不咸了
But then the salt turns out to be not very salty.
# 我们可能吃三袋吃四袋
Then maybe we will need 3 or 4 bags.
# 所以也是一种创造经济效益的一种方式
So this is also a way to generate economic returns.
# 但是说我们
However, when we
# 真正要腌菜腌韭菜花
really want to cure vegetables, like chive flower,
# 腌泡菜
kimchi,
# 腌咸菜
pickles,
# 一定要用大粒盐
we have to use large grain salt.
# 另外有些腌泡菜腌咸菜
Besides, sometimes when we cure kimchi or pickles,
# 为什么要加花椒
we add Sichuan pepper. The reason is
# 它也是防腐
it is also a preservative.
# 有的还要加点白酒
Some needs a bit of Baijiu.
# 也是防腐
This is also for preservation.
# 有的还要加点红糖或者冰糖
Some needs a bit of brown sugar or white rock sugar.
# 也是防腐
This is again for preservation.
# 而且还能滋润我们的口感
It also mellows the mouthfeel,
# 使咸不是那么愣
which makes the saltiness less dull,
# 齁咸
or extremely salty.
# 加点糖会把它(口感)综合一点
A bit of sugar can merge the tastes.
# 使菜腌出来以后
So that when the vegetable is cured,
# 一是不容易坏
on the one hand, it is less prone to going bad.
# 另外的口感会更好
Secondly, the mouthfeel will be improved.
# 另外我们还要提醒我们网友
In addition, we have to remind our audience that,
# 在腌菜的时候
when you cure vegetables,
# 大家一定要注意
you have to pay attention that
# 腌咸菜不能少于15天
the curing process cannot be less than 15 days.
# 而且在7天到10天之内
And when it’s between 7-10 days,
# 它的亚硝酸盐是最重的
it has the highest amount of nitrite.
# 有时候容易吃多了
Sometimes if you have too much of it,
# 还容易中毒
you may be poisoned.